｢There was a hungry crow｣
♪ ｢お 腹 空 かせた ｶﾗｽがいた｣
｢who wanted to get some feed｣
♪ ｢なんとか 餌 に ありつきたい｣
｢If only this beak were longer｣
♪ ｢この くちばしが もっと長ければ｣
｢That feed would be a bit closer.｣
♪ ｢あの餌が もっと こっちに来れば｣
♪ ～
♪ ～
｢a crow can think｣
｢ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える｣
｢can think... can think｣
♪ ｢考える 考える｣
Observe, propose a hypothesis, experiment and consider results.
( 斎藤 )観察し 仮 説を立て 実験をし 考察する｡
Learn the way of scientific thought.
科学の考え方を学べ｡
We begin with a ｢Thinking Observation｣.
(山本)まずは ｢考える観察｣から｡
If we make a loop out of paper, and cut through the middle with scissors...
紙で輪っかを作って ﾊｻﾐで真ん中を切ると…｡
It becomes two rings.
２個に 分かれる｡
Today we will be observing this.
今日は これを観察する｡
This time we give it a half turn before attach it.
今度は 半回転ひねって くっつける｡
And if we cut right down the middle with a pair of scissors...
これの真ん中を ﾊｻﾐで切っていくと…｡
it's twisted but it becomes one big loop.
ねじれているが １個の大きい輪っかになった｡
Next, after an initial half turn, we give it one further half turn.
次は 半回転ひねって もう半回転｡
In total it's turned one full time, let's try cutting it.
合計 １回転ひねって 切ってみる｡
It became two rings.
２個の輪っかになった｡
It's twisted but it's two.
つながっているが 輪っかは ２個だ｡
Why did the ring sometimes become one ring and sometimes two?
なぜ 輪っかは １個だったり ２個だったりするのか？
Let's try observing with color applied to both edges of the strip.
帯の両わきを 色でぬり分けて 観察してみる｡
When we give it a half twist, it's connected like this.
半回転ひねりだと こんなふうに つながっている｡
If we traverse from here, red connects to blue.
ここから たどっていくと 赤は 青につながっていて →
And going around, it's connected to back to red.
ぐるっと回って 赤につながって
We return to our inital position.
元の位置に もどってくる｡
Is it that the red and blue line at the strinp's edge
という事は 帯の両わきの赤と青の線は →
is connected as one?
一本で つながっている？
And thus...
それで…｡
it becomes one single loop?
１つの輪っかになるのか？
Then what happened when we gave it a full turn?
では 一回転ひねった時は どうなっていたのか？
Connecting red to red,
赤は 赤どうし つながっていて →
and blue connecting to blue.
青は 青どうし つながっている｡
If we cut this...
これを切ると…｡
It becomes two loops, red and blue.
赤と青の ２つの輪っかになる｡
Then what will happen in this case?
じゃあ こういう場合は どうなるのか？
We draw three lines and connect a loop with a half turn.
３本 線を引いて 半回転ひねって くっつける｡
If we cut the white part in the space between the lines
そして 線の間の白い部分を切ると →
How many rings will will there be?
輪っかは 何個 できるのか？
If we look at the place they join, first red and yellow...
つなぎ目を見ると 赤は黄色に →
then yellow is connected to red.
この黄色は 赤につながっている｡
Blue is only connected to blue.
青は 青だけで つながっている｡
What will happen?
どうなるのか？
♪ ～
♪ ～
Today's problem deals with a spool of thread.
( 蒼井 )今日は この糸まきを使った問題です｡
The spool rests on a desk.
つくえの上に 糸まきを置きます｡
There's a little thread coming out.
少し 糸が出ています｡
Now, this is the problem.
さて ここからが問題です｡
We pull the thread, like this
この糸を このように引っぱります｡
How will the spool move?
糸まきは どう動くでしょうか？
1. The spool will move away from our hand.
１ こう回転して 手から はなれる｡
2. The reverse. It will go this way.
２ ぎゃくに こっち向きに回転して →
Getting nearer to the hand that's pulling.
引っぱった手に 近づく｡
3. It will spin in place without moving.
３ その場で空回りして動かない｡
We'll show the answer at the end of the program.
答えは 番組の最後に発表します｡
How will the spool move?
糸まきが どう動くか →
Everyone think really hard, okay?
みなさん よ～く考えておいて下さいね｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
Observation, hypothesis, experiment, and reflection.
観察 仮説 実験 そして考察｡
Thinking scientifically...
科学の考え方…
And now the answer from earlier.
では 先ほどの答えです｡
Everyone did you think carefully?
みなさん ちゃ～んと考えましたか？
1. It will move away from our hand.
１ 手から はなれる｡
2. It will move closer to the hand pulling.
２ 引っぱった手に 近づく｡
3. It will turn in place without moving.
３ その場で空回りして動かない｡
What will happen? Watch carefully, please.
どうなるか よ～く見ていて下さいね｡
Then...
では…｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
The spool moved towards the hand pullin the thread.
糸まきは 引っぱった手の方向に 転がってきました｡
Let's try that once more.
もう一度 やってみましょう｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
As we thought, it moved in the direction we're pulling.
やっぱり 引っぱった方向に 転がってきました｡
This time, let's try changing the size.
では 今度は 大きさを変えてやってみましょう｡
Let's try this small spool of thread.
この 小さな糸まきで やってみます｡
Let's go.
いきますよ｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
As we thought it moves twoards the hand pulling the thread.
やっぱり 引っぱった手の方向に 転がってきました｡
As this is very curious,
これは とても おもしろいので →
everyone, please try it at home.
みなさん 家で やってみて下さいね｡
But why should it do that?
でも どうして こうなるのでしょう？
This is the spool's...
それは この糸まきの…｡
From here on we think for ourselves.
ここから先は 自分で考えよう｡
From here on evryone on is a thinking crow.
これからは みんなが ｢考えるｶﾗｽ｣｡